Operations and Management Area Working Group                     T. Dahm
Internet-Draft                                                          
Updates: 8907 (if approved)                                   J. Heasley
Intended status: Standards Track                                     NTT
Expires: 8 October 2026                                 D.C. Medway Gash
                                                     Cisco Systems, Inc.
                                                                  A. Ota
                                                             Google Inc.
                                                            6 April 2026


  SSH Public Key Distribution for Device Administration using Terminal
         Access Controller Access-Control System Plus (TACACS+)
                          draft-tacacs-ssh-00

Abstract

   SSH [RFC4251] provides robust and reliable mechanism to connect to
   Network Devices for administration.  Conventionally, the Public Keys
   required to authenticate SSH sessions are provisioned directly on the
   Network Devices.  This document adds an extension into Terminal
   Access Controller Access-Control System Plus (TACACS+) to replace the
   need for the direct provisioning of SSH public keys onto the Network
   Devices.

Requirements Language

   The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
   "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
   14 [RFC2119] [RFC8174] when, and only when, they appear in all
   capitals, as shown here.

Status of This Memo

   This Internet-Draft is submitted in full conformance with the
   provisions of BCP 78 and BCP 79.

   Internet-Drafts are working documents of the Internet Engineering
   Task Force (IETF).  Note that other groups may also distribute
   working documents as Internet-Drafts.  The list of current Internet-
   Drafts is at https://datatracker.ietf.org/drafts/current/.

   Internet-Drafts are draft documents valid for a maximum of six months
   and may be updated, replaced, or obsoleted by other documents at any
   time.  It is inappropriate to use Internet-Drafts as reference
   material or to cite them other than as "work in progress."




Dahm, et al.             Expires 8 October 2026                 [Page 1]

Internet-Draft  SSH Public Key Distribution for Device A      April 2026


   This Internet-Draft will expire on 8 October 2026.

Copyright Notice

   Copyright (c) 2026 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the
   document authors.  All rights reserved.

   This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust's Legal
   Provisions Relating to IETF Documents (https://trustee.ietf.org/
   license-info) in effect on the date of publication of this document.
   Please review these documents carefully, as they describe your rights
   and restrictions with respect to this document.  Code Components
   extracted from this document must include Revised BSD License text as
   described in Section 4.e of the Trust Legal Provisions and are
   provided without warranty as described in the Revised BSD License.

Table of Contents

   1.  Introduction  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   2
   2.  Technical Definitions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   3
     2.1.  SSHST+  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   3
   3.  SSH Public Key Distribution . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   3
     3.1.  Authentication START Packet . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   3
     3.2.  Authentication REPLY Packet . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   3
     3.3.  SSH Key download process  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   3
   4.  Security Considerations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   4
   5.  Operational Considerations  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   4
   6.  IANA Considerations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   5
   7.  Normative References  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   5
   8.  Normative References  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   5
   Appendix A.  Appendix 1 [REPLACE/DELETE]  . . . . . . . . . . . .   5
   Acknowledgements  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   5
   Contributors  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   5
   Authors' Addresses  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .   5

1.  Introduction

   SSH provides robust and reliable mechanism to connect to Network
   Devices for administration.  The widespread approach to provisioning
   the Public Keys required to authenticate SSH sessions is to upload
   them through some administration interface onto the Network Devices
   which are acting as SSH Server.  Once an SSH connection has been
   established, the Device Administration session is then often mediated
   (authorized and audited) through protocols such as Terminal Access
   Controller Access-Control System Plus (TACACS+) Protocol via one or
   more centralised Servers.





Dahm, et al.             Expires 8 October 2026                 [Page 2]

Internet-Draft  SSH Public Key Distribution for Device A      April 2026


   This document describes an enhancement of the secured version of the
   TACACS+ protocol [RFC9887] to facilitate the download of the 
   applicable Public Keys from a central TACACS+ server so that the
   TACACS+ Client can use it to complete SSH authentication.
   The intent is to shift the burden of administration of SSH Public
   Keys from the Network Devices to the central TACACS+ Server.
   Note that this model does NOT extend the SSH authentication flow
   out from the SSH Server (The TACACS+ Client), to the TACACS+ 
   Server.  The authentication remains completely in the SSH
   Server (The TACACS+ Client).  It is important to keep this in mind,
   as the phase of the AAA protocol that is used to download the public
   Keys is actually the TACACS+ Authentication phase.

   Specifically, this document adds a new authentication action value
   into TACACS+ Authnentication flow, the reply to which, allows the
   TACACS+ Server to send the relevant SSH Public Keys to the device.

2.  Technical Definitions

   The terms defined in Section 2 of [RFC9887] are fully applicable here
   and will not be repeated.  The following terms are also used in this document.

2.1.  SSHST+

   An SSHST+ (SSH Server/TACACS+ Client).  This is the device that is
   running the SSH Server and is configured as a TACACS+ Client.

3.  SSH Public Key Distribution

   The following mechanism describes the process. This enhancement of TACACS+
   Protocol is only applicable to the TLS TACACS+ protocol.

3.1.  Authentication START Packet

   A new enumerated value is added for use within the action field of the 
   Authentication START Packet:

   TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_SEND_PUBLIC_KEYS := 0x05

3.2.  Authentication REPLY Packet

   A New enumerated value is added for use within the status section of the 
   Authentication REPLY Packet:

   TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_STATUS_MORE := 0x22

3.2.  SSH Key download process

   As a result of SSH connection attempt, an SSHST+ requires the public
   key for a user.





Dahm, et al.             Expires 8 October 2026                 [Page 3]

Internet-Draft  SSH Public Key Distribution for Device A      April 2026


   If no key is available, then it MAY initiate a TACACS+
   Authentication flow to retrieve the key from the TACACS+ Server.

   SSHST+ sends an Authentication Start packet with the action field set
   to TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_SEND_PUBLIC_KEYS defined in Section 3.1:

   1.  user = username

   2.  action = TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_SEND_PUBLIC_KEYS

   3.  priv_lvl = 0 XXX This field might not be 0; right?

   4.  authen_type = TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_TYPE_ASCII

   5.  service = TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_SVC_LOGIN

   The user field of the Authentication Start packet contains the
   username for which the public keys are required.

   The TACACS+ Server processes the start packet, extracting the
   username, and determines if it can provide the public keys which are
   applicable for the username. The source of public keys is not defined by
   this document.

   If public keys are not available, the server responds with
   status=TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_STATUS_FAIL.

   If public keys are available, the server responds with
   status=TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_STATUS_PASS if there is only one applicable key or
   TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_STATUS_MORE if there are more than one key. The Public Keys are encoded
   into the data field as described in Section 3.3.

   1.  status = TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_STATUS_PASS

   2.  server_msg = EMPTY

   3.  data (section 3.3)

   XXX We had a proposal for this; "PASS" seems weird.

   SSHST+ receives the Authentication Reply packet and extracts the
   public key from the data field.

   SSHST+ uses the public key to authenticate the user.  If there is a failure,
   but the status is TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_STATUS_MORE, then the SSHST+ can
   Send Authentication CONTINUE Packet with the data field set to the last SSH Key that was 
   Returned. The cycle can continue until the authentication passes or the Server runs out of keys. 
   When the TACACS+ Server sends the last key (or first key if there is only one), 
   it MUST respond with TAC_PLUS_AUTHEN_STATUS_PASS.

   XXX Comment/guidance about caching keys should be added.  Can a client
   cache?  for how long?  Does a tacacs flag control this?

   Authorisation and Accounting proceed as they would if the SSH key had been 
   provisioned by the administrator directly onto the SSHST+.

3.3 Encoding of SSH Public Key in Authentication Reply Packet

   The Public Key is encoded in the data field of the Authentication Reply 
   Packet as follows:

   1. The encoding as Text String and must conform to Section 3.7 of [rfc8907]

   2. The content is limited to 32716 characters. Any larger, the key MUST be treated
      as unavailable as described in section 3.2

   3. The syntax of the encoding MUST conform to [rfc4716] (OK, do we want thsi 
      Or the more common implementation in the field, that ignored this RFC)?

    XXX This requires much more thought.  maybe both should be supported?

4.  Security Considerations

   This exertion MUST only be implemented in Secured TACACS+, as defined in [RFC9887]

   XXX why?  do we care?  Is there something about the protocol change that
   requires TLS or that is more exposed than the password mechanism?  By
   this, I mean suggest holding the gun at the correct end, but your
   prerogative.

5.  Operational Considerations

   TBD






Dahm, et al.             Expires 8 October 2026                 [Page 4]

Internet-Draft  SSH Public Key Distribution for Device A      April 2026


6.  IANA Considerations

   TBD

7.  Normative References

   [RFC2119]  Bradner, S., "Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
              Requirement Levels", BCP 14, RFC 2119,
              DOI 10.17487/RFC2119, March 1997,
              <https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119>.

   [RFC8174]  Leiba, B., "Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC
              2119 Key Words", BCP 14, RFC 8174, DOI 10.17487/RFC8174,
              May 2017, <https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174>.

   [RFC8907]  Dahm, T., Ota, A., Medway Gash, D.C., Carrel, D., and L.
              Grant, "The Terminal Access Controller Access-Control
              System Plus (TACACS+) Protocol", RFC 8907,
              DOI 10.17487/RFC8907, September 2020,
              <https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8907>.

   [RFC9887]   

   [RFC4716]

    

8.  Normative References

   [RFC4251]  Ylonen, T. and C. Lonvick, Ed., "The Secure Shell (SSH)
              Protocol Architecture", RFC 4251, DOI 10.17487/RFC4251,
              January 2006, <https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4251>.

    

Appendix A.  Appendix 1 [REPLACE/DELETE]

   This becomes an Appendix [REPLACE]

Acknowledgements

   This template uses extracts from templates written by Pekka Savola,
   Elwyn Davies and Henrik Levkowetz.  [REPLACE]

Contributors

   Thanks to all of the contributors.  [REPLACE]

Authors' Addresses

   Thorsten Dahm
   Email: thorsten.dahm@gmail.com


   John Heasley
   NTT



Dahm, et al.             Expires 8 October 2026                 [Page 5]

Internet-Draft  SSH Public Key Distribution for Device A      April 2026


   Email: heas@shrubbery.net


   Douglas C. Medway Gash
   Cisco Systems, Inc.
   170 West Tasman Dr.
   San Jose, CA 95134
   United States of America
   Email: dcmgash@cisco.com


   Andrej Ota
   Google Inc.
   1600 Amphitheatre Parkway
   Mountain View, CA 94043
   United States of America
   Email: andrej@ota.si


































Dahm, et al.             Expires 8 October 2026                 [Page 6]
